<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>

<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" >
  <generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="3.8.5">Jekyll</generator>
  <link href="https://ricardocosteira.com/tag/talks/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" />
  <link href="https://ricardocosteira.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" />
  <updated>2020-03-09T12:12:37+00:00</updated>
  <id>https://ricardocosteira.com/tag/talks/feed.xml</id>

  
  
  

  
    <title type="html">Ricardo Costeira | </title>
  

  
    <subtitle>A mobile software engineer with a passion for Android and clean, maintainable code. I build apps from the ground up and maintain existing ones.</subtitle>
  

  

  
    
      
    
  

  
  

  
    <entry>
      <title type="html">My talk about Kotlin Flow at DevFest Leiria 2019</title>
      <link href="https://ricardocosteira.com/my-talk-about-kotlin-flow-at-devfest-leiria-2019" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="My talk about Kotlin Flow at DevFest Leiria 2019" />
      <published>2019-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</published>
      <updated>2019-12-23T00:00:00+00:00</updated>
      <id>https://ricardocosteira.com/my-talk-about-kotlin-flow-at-devfest-leiria-2019</id>
      <content type="html" xml:base="https://ricardocosteira.com/my-talk-about-kotlin-flow-at-devfest-leiria-2019">&lt;p&gt;On December 14 of 2019, I gave a talk about Kotlin Flow at DevFest Leiria.
My main motivation for wanting to give this talk was simple: reactive programming is here to stay.
Most Android devs nowadays are used to sprinkle RxJava throughout their apps, even if they don’t actually have use for reactive streams and just want to simplify thread scheduling. However, it’s also true that more and more devs are becoming aware that Rx is an overkill for their use case, and long for better options.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kotlin Flow is one of the new additions to the Kotlin coroutines library, and is meant to bring reactive streams to the coroutine world. But is it as powerful as RxJava?
In this talk, I explored what Kotlin Flow is, how can it be used, and how can it imbue our apps with the power of reactive programming.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;hr /&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I had a great time. GDG Leiria managed to pull off a wonderful event, and it was their first DevFest! You can find a link to the slides &lt;a href=&quot;https://speakerdeck.com/rcosteira79/do-you-even-kotlin-flow-the-new-api-for-reactive-programming&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, and a link to the event page &lt;a href=&quot;https://devfest.gdgleiria.xyz/&quot;&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Thank you for reading!&lt;/p&gt;</content>

      
      
      
      
      

      <author>
          <name>Ricardo Costeira</name>
        
        
      </author>

      

      
        <category term="Android" />
      
        <category term="Talks" />
      

      
        <summary type="html">On December 14 of 2019, I gave a talk about Kotlin Flow at DevFest Leiria. My main motivation for wanting to give this talk was simple: reactive programming is here to stay. Most Android devs nowadays are used to sprinkle RxJava throughout their apps, even if they don’t actually have use for reactive streams and just want to simplify thread scheduling. However, it’s also true that more and more devs are becoming aware that Rx is an overkill for their use case, and long for better options.</summary>
      

      
      
    </entry>
  
</feed>
